A Guide to the The Ladies Board, 1912-
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
The Ladies Board of Inova Loudoun Hospital 1912-
Thomas Balch Library
M 049, VC 0040, OMB 0010
This collection includes scrapbooks, annual reports, news articles, and photographs tracing the activities of The Ladies Board (TLB) from its founding in 1912 until 2010. Most of the records are from 1964 to 2010. It is an open collection since the board is still active in supporting Inova Loudoun Hospital. Early records are very sketchy and most of the information is found in brief histories of TLB written by early, unidentified members of the board.
The Ladies Board of Inova Loudoun Hospital, Leesburg, VA.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Ladies Board of Inova Loudoun Hospital, Leesburg, VA.
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2008.0047, 2012.0039
Historical Information
Leesburg Hospital, Inc. (now Inova Loudoun Hospital)*, was originally located on Market Street in Leesburg, VA. It was established in 1912 by Dr. William Clayton Orr (1878-1926), President, and Dr. John A. Gibson (1876-1947), Vice President. The Ladies Board (TLB) was organized the same year to provide volunteer supervision of housekeeping and to provide fund raising. The board, originally composed of forty women representing various areas of Loudoun County and called the Ladies Board of Managers, was headed by Mrs. William Cochran Eustis (Edith Livingston Morton) (1874-1964) who served as president until 1919. It is unclear when the name of the Ladies Board of Managers was changed to The Ladies Board, but it seems to have been in 1912 or 1913. In time the volunteers on TLB not only oversaw housekeeping, they also supplied china, glassware, and silver for the dining room, kitchen equipment, and supplies for beds, rooms, and wards. From 1926 until 1932 a primary concern of TLB was furnishing and maintaining a home for nurses.
In order to raise money for these projects, TLB held the first of its rummage sales in 1938 at St. James Episcopal Church in Leesburg, VA; total profit that year was $150.00. This annual sale, which has become the largest fund-raising event of TLB, outgrew St. James Episcopal Church, moved to the 4-H Fairgrounds, and later to Morven Park Equestrian Center in Leesburg. In 2010, proceeds from the rummage sale totaled more than $150,000.00.
A Penny Fund, now called Polly Clemens Nursery Fund for its long-time chair, was started to fund needs of The Birthing Inn at the hospital's Lansdowne location. The facility is called The Ladies Board of Loudoun Inova Hospital Birthing Inn in recognition of TLB. Other fund-raising ventures include the Ladies Board Gift Shop established in 1974, first located in the hospital at Cornwall Street in Leesburg and now at Inova Loudoun Hospital's Lansdowne location. In 1990 TLB opened a thrift shop, Twice Is Nice, currently located at 305 East Market Street in Leesburg. To help raise money for nursing scholarships given by TLB, a Lights of Love program was established in 1983. Lights of Love offers a way to honor or remember people who have made a difference in one's life by making a donation to the program; all donations go toward nursing scholarships.
Funds from all of these activities are donated to various departments of Inova Loudoun Hospital, and have funded many projects contributing to patient care and treatment through the years.
*Inova Loudoun Hospital - History of Name Changes
5 June 1912: Leesburg Hospital, Inc.
1914: Loudoun Hospital, Inc.
1930: Loudoun County Hospital
1964: Loudoun Memorial Hospital
1985: Loudoun Healthcare, Inc. - parent company established
1988: Loudoun Hospital Center
21 October 2004: Loudoun Healthcare begins merger with Inova Health System
March 2005: Inova Loudoun Hospital
Scope and Content
This collection includes scrapbooks, annual reports, news articles, and photographs tracing the activities of The Ladies Board (TLB) from its founding in 1912 until 2009. Most of the records are from 1964 to 2009. It is an open collection since the board is still active in supporting Inova Loudoun Hospital. Early records are very sketchy and most of the information is found in brief histories of TLB written by early, unidentified members of the board. Annual reports for eight years were copied from the personal files of Kay B. Stowers of Leesburg, VA; these have been noted in the container list. Loose materials were removed from scrapbooks or manila envelopes and placed in file folders. Envelopes of photographs were removed to VC 0040. Manuscript relocation sheets have been inserted in scrapbooks from which materials and photographs were removed. Materials from 1996, 1997, and 2001 were not kept in scrapbooks but in brown accordion files from which they were removed to the files indicated. Materials for 1995 and 1998-2002 were kept in manila envelopes from which they were removed to the files indicated. In several instances miscellaneous materials were in manila envelopes inserted in scrapbooks. These materials were removed to files and relocation sheets have been placed in the scrapbook and the original location has been noted in the container list.
Arrangement
Box folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Ancestry Library Edition, United States Census, United States Census and Voter Lists, http://www.ancestrylibrary.com (accessed 20 June 2011).
Inova Loudoun Hospital Foundation, Leesburg, VA.
Ladies Board of Inova Loudoun Hospital Birthing Inn, http://www.thebirthinginn.org/
Loudoun Cemetery Database. http://www.leesburgva.gov/index.aspx?page=940 (accessed 20 June 2011).
Oatlands Historic House and Gardens, http://www.oatlands.org/photog/list.asp?ID=2 (accessed 20 June 2011)
The Ladies Board of Inova Loudoun Hospital, 1912- (M 049), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
Ancestry Library Edition, United States Census, United States Census and Voter Lists, http://www.ancestrylibrary.com (accessed 20 June 2011).
Related Material
None
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - (Inserted materials removed from envelope in front cover of Scrapbook 1927-1964). Brochure promoting campaign to raise money to build hospital, 1913; 1917 photograph of new hospital; newspaper article re: construction of hospital; early histories of TLB-authors unknown; article re: hospital garden by Penelope M. Osburn (1900-1976), n.d., 1912-1919
  - (Inserted materials removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, p.89) Annual Report of Loudoun County Hospital, 1928 & 1929; photographs and newspaper articles, 1920s-1930s
  - (Inserted materials removed from envelope in front cover of Scrapbook 1927-1964) Proposal offered by Finance Committee of TLB, 1940s; proposed script for radio broadcast 21 June 1946 re: Loudoun County Hospital, 1940s
  - (Inserted materials removed from envelope in front cover of scrapbook 1927-1964) Newspaper clippings; rummage sale report, 1950s
  - (Inserted materials removed from envelope in front cover of Scrapbook 1927-1964) Copy of Loudoun Times Mirror section of 2 June 1960 celebrating dedication of new hospital; newspaper articles, 1960s
  - (Inserted materials removed from Scrapbook 1927-1964, pp. 38-39) List of officers and members of TLB, 4 June 1960
  - (Inserted materials removed from envelope labeled 1963-65 inside back cover of Scrapbook 1964-1966) History of TLB; memo re: Rummage Sale; report of income and expenditures of rummage sale, 1969
  - (Inserted materials removed from inside front cover of Scrapbook 1966-1974) Annual Report, July 1966
  - (Inserted material removed from inside front cover of Scrapbook 1966-1974) Annual Report, July 1967
  - (Inserted material removed from inside front cover of Scrapbook 1966-1974) Annual Report, July 1968
  - (Inserted material removed from inside front cover of Scrapbook 1966-1974) Annual Report, July 1969
  - (Inserted material removed from inside front cover of Scrapbook 1966-74) Annual Report, July 1970
  - (Inserted material removed from inside front cover of Scrapbook 1966-74) Annual Report, July 1971
  - (Copied from personal files of Kay Stowers) Annual Report, July 1972
  - (Inserted material removed from inside front cover of Scrapbook 1966-1974) Annual Report, July 1973
  - (Inserted material removed from inside front cover of Scrapbook 1971-1974) Dedication Edition, Loudoun Times Mirror, 27 June 1974
  - (Inserted material removed from back of Scrapbook 1971-1974 before folder labeled "Dedication Newspapers") Tour of new hospital on Cornwall Street, Leesburg, VA; map of hospital
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1970s, pp. 4-5) Annual Report, July 1974
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1970s, pp. 18-19) Annual Report, July 1975
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1970s, pp. 62-63) Annual Report, July 1976
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1970s, pp. 68-69) Annual Report, July 1977
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1970s, pp. 104-105) Annual Report, July 1978
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1970s, pp. 108-109) Annual Report; 8 photographs, p.110, July 1979
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1970s, pp. 122-123) Annual Report, July 1980
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1980-1986, pp. 30-31) Annual Report, July 1981
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1980-1986, pp. 54-55) Annual Report, July 1982
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report, 1983
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1980-1986, pp. 68-69, envelope 1984) Newspaper articles; correspondence re: cycle chair
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report, 1984
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1980-1986, inside back cover, envelope 1985) Press releases; letter re: membership on TLB; advertisements re: opening of Medex
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report, 1985
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report, 1986
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report, 1987
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, inside front cover) List of officers and members 1988-1990; press releases and newspaper articles
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp. 3-4) Photograph of officers; newspaper article
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report, 1988
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report
- (Box 2)
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp. 52-53) Newspaper articles
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp 56-57) Press releases, newspaper articles
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp 56-57) Annual Report, July 1990
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp 58-59) List of officers and members, 1990-1992
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp. 72-73)
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp. 80-81) Press releases; photographs; Loudoun HealthLink
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp. 82-83) Article from Loudoun HealthLink
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp.84-85) Newspaper photograph concerning opening of Twice Is Nice
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp.88-89) Annual Report, July 1991; By-Laws; The Loudoun County Hospital Project 1946; copy of Auxiliary Prayer
  - (Inserted material removed from Scrapbook 1988-1992, pp. 110-111) Virginia Association of Hospital Auxiliaries 1949-1991; news articles; copies of Loudoun HealthLink
  - (Inserted materials removed from envelope labeled 1992, Scrapbook 1988-1992, inside back cover) Commemorative newspaper, 17 September 1992; news articles; copies of Loudoun HealthLink
  - (Inserted material removed from front cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994) List of officers and members, 1993-1994
  - (Inserted material removed from envelope labeled 1993, Scrapbook 1992-1994, pp. 64-65) Press releases; newspaper articles
  - (Inserted material removed from 1994 envelope in back cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994) Annual Report July 1994; list of officers and members 1993-1994; By-Laws
  - (Inserted material removed from envelope labeled in back cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994) Newspaper articles; photographs; site plan for new hospital at Lansdowne
  - (Inserted material removed from envelope 1995) News Articles; copies of InterCom; Annual Report, July 1995
  - (Inserted material removed from brown accordion file 1996) Press releases and newspaper articles; article on opening of therapeutic pool; copy of InterCom; Annual Report, July 1996
  - (Inserted material removed from brown accordion file 1997) Newspaper articles; Annual Report July 1997; dedication program for Loudoun Hospital Center at Lansdowne; list of officers and members, 1997-1998
  - (Inserted material removed from envelope 1998) Newspaper articles; rummage sale information; invitations and brochures; list of officers and members, 1996-1998; grants for hospital projects
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report, 1998
  - (Inserted material removed from envelope 1999) Annual Report July 1999; rummage sale ad and information; Penny Fund photograph and information
- (Box 3)
  - (Copied from files of Kay B. Stowers) Annual Report, July 2000
  - (Inserted material removed from envelope 2000) Annual Report 2000-2001; proposed budget July 2001-2002; list of officers and members 2000-2001; revised By-Laws 2000; newspaper articles
  - (Inserted material removed from envelope 2001) List of officers and members 2001-2002; proposed budget 2001-2002; rummage sale advertisement; Lights of Love brochure
  - (Inserted materials removed from envelope 2002) Program from ground breaking for Birthing Inn; rummage sale advertisement and information; Loudoun Magazine (article regarding rummage sale); calendar 2002 - Native American
  - (From Ladies Board Office) Annual Report, July 2003
  - (From Ladies Board Office) Annual Report, July 2004
  - (From Ladies Board Office) Annual Report, July 2009
  - Newspaper articles regarding Rummage Sales, 1973-1978, 1982
- (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook 1927-1964
  - Scrapbook 1964-1966
  - Scrapbook 1966-1974
  - Scrapbook 1971-1974
  - Scrapbook 1970s (1974-1980)
  - Scrapbook 1980-1986
- (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook 1988-1992
  - Scrapbook 1992-1994
  - Scrapbook 1996
  - Scrapbook 2003-2006
  - Scrapbook 2006-2007
- (Box 6)
  - Scrapbook 2008-2010
- (OMB 010)
  - Scrapbook, 1986-1988
  - Scrapbook, 2007-2008
- (VC 40)
- (Box 1)
  - (removed from Scrapbook 1970s, p. 120) 10 Miler (20), 1980
  - (removed from envelope labeled 1985 in back cover of Scrapbook 1980-1986): Rummage sale (3); donation to hospital (1); Lights of Love (1), 1985
  - (removed from envelope labeled 1992 in back of Scrapbook 1998-1992): Officers (1); Lights of Love (18), 1988
  - (removed from envelope 1990): Lights of Love (7), 1990
  - (removed from picture album 1992): Rummage sale (24), 1991
  - (removed from picture album 1992): Lights of Love (8), 1991
  - (removed from picture album1992): Twice is Nice (7), 1992
  - (removed from picture album1992): Rummage sale (49), 1992
  - (removed from envelope 1992): Harvest Tea (5), 1992
  - (removed from envelope labeled 1993 inserted in front cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994): Rummage sale (57), 1993
  - (removed from envelope labeled 1993 inserted in front cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994): Luncheon (6), 1993
  - (removed from envelope labeled 1993 inserted in Scrapbook 1992-1994, pp. 64-65): Tea (5); donation to hospital (1); officers (1), 1993
  - (removed from envelope labeled 1994 inserted in back cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994): Ribbon cutting (1), 1994
  - (removed from envelope labeled 1994 inserted in back cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994): Luncheon (9), 1994
  - (removed from envelope 1994 inserted in back cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994): Lights of Love (26), 1994
  - (removed from photo envelope 1954 [sic]) 1994): Rummage sale (29), 1994
  - (removed from envelope labeled 1994 in back cover of Scrapbook 1992-1994): Officers (1), 1995
  - (removed from envelope 1995): Rummage sale (24), 1995
  - (removed from top of brown accordion file 1996): Tour of new hospital (9), 1996
  - (removed from brown accordion file 1996 after paper marked "very important"): Therapeutic pool opening (35), 1996
  - (removed from brown accordion file 1996 after pictures clipped together in white envelope): Lights of Love (31), 1996
  - (removed from 1996 brown accordion file after Rummage Sale Report): Rummage sale (37), 1996
  - (removed from brown accordion folder 1996 after article and picture of officers): Donation to hospital (3), 1996
  - (removed from brown accordion folder 1996 after article on nursing scholarships): Tea (8), 1996
- (Box 2)
  - (removed from 1997 brown accordion file): Nursing scholarship presentation (3), Polly Clemens Penny Fund (4), van purchase (2), 1997
  - (removed from 1997 brown accordion file): Lights of Love (36), 1997
  - (removed from 1997 brown accordion file): Tour of new hospital--Lansdowne (9), 1997
  - (removed from 1997 brown accordion file): Gift Shop (12), 1997
  - (removed from 1997 brown accordion file): Rummage sale (28), 1997
  - (removed from 1998 brown accordion file): Officers (1); Gift Shop (1); presentation of proceeds from rummage sale (1); Twice is Nice (1), 1998
  - (removed from 1998 brown accordion file): Luncheon (8), 1998
  - (removed from 1999 brown accordion file): Rummage sale (6), 1999
  - (removed from 2000 brown accordion file): Luncheon (2), 2000
  - (removed from 2000 brown accordion file): Rummage sale (74), 2000
  - (removed from 2001 envelope): Rummage sale (35), 2001
  - (removed from 2002 brown accordion file): Rummage sale (99), 2002
  - Gift Shop (15), 2002
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 2003-2006; pp 60-61): Twice is Nice (3), 2005
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 2003-2006; pp 60-61): Rummage sale (25), 2005
  - (Removed from Scrapbook 2003-2006; pp 70-71): Lights of Love (1); luncheon (1), 2005
  - Gift Shop (21), (n.d.)
  - Rummage sale (50), 2002?
- (Box 3)
  - Negatives of photographs from 1990, 1992-1994, 1996-1997; duplicate photographs